Really?
真的
Did the doctor
医生
actually say that?
真的这么说的
Yes, he did.
真的呀
He said that this time the medication
医生说这次用药
has shown significant improvement.
效果有明显的改善
You can be discharged and go home.
您可以出院休养
In a few days,
过几天呢
we'll help you with the procedures.
我们帮你办理出院
Then we can go home.
然后咱们就回家
It's great to be able to go home.
能回家太好了
That's fantastic!
太好了
Could
那
you please
那麻烦你们
help me clear out
帮我把老房子
the old house?
收拾出来
What's wrong, mom?
怎么了妈
Do you hate me or something?
你讨厌我呀
Don't you want to live with me?
不想跟我一起住啊
What are you saying, my dear?
你这孩子这说什么呢
I like you more than anything.
我喜欢你还来不及呢
As long as you don't hate me,
那你不讨厌我的话就行
I'll stay with you
那我陪您
in the old house.
回老房子住
That's not a good idea!
这怎么可以啊
You two
你们这
are newlyweds.
刚结婚的小夫妻
How can I let you stay with me?
我怎么能让你陪我呢
Why not?
那怎么不行呀
You see, you don't want
你看你不愿意
to live with us,
跟我们一起住
which means
说明
you must hate one of us.
你肯定讨厌哪个人吧
If it's not me,
那不是我的话
it must be him.
肯定是他啦
Anyway,
反正呢
we won't push you.
我们不会勉强你
But we can't
但是又不能
let you live on your own.
让你一个人住
So I'll have to stay with you.
所以只能我陪着你了
No, Xiaoning,
不是啊筱柠
I...
我
I didn't mean it that way.
我不是这个意思
What I meant was...
我是
That's not what you meant?
不是这个意思呀
Then let's just go home.
那咱们就回家住吧
It's settled then.
就这么说定了
You little rascal,
你这小脑袋瓜呀
play all these little tricks on me.
心思全用在妈妈身上了
I'm just teasing you.
逗你玩玩吗
Cheer up a little.
高兴一下
Come home, alright?
回家住啊
[It's a deal.]
说好了
Hey.
亲家
Hey, you guys are here.
亲家来了
Dad, mom.
爸 妈
Yuheng.
小纪
How're you doing?
怎么样啊
Pretty good.
挺好的
I'll take that.
给我 给我
I cooked mushroom soup for you.
给你炖的蘑菇汤
[I was trying to make some chicken soup.]
本来想炖个鸡汤
[I bought the chicken,]
鸡都买了
but she wouldn't let me.
她不让炖
She's going through "immunocetechemistry,"
亲家这免组疫化
so she can't take in estrogen.
不能补雌激素
Chicken soup is no good to her.
你还弄鸡汤
That's really absurd.
真胡来
Isn't it?
是不是啊
Taking chicken soup
喝鸡汤啊
to boost estrogen is just pseudoscience.
能补雌激素那是伪科学
Besides,
而且啊
that's called immunocytochemistry,
那叫免疫组化
not immunocetechemistry.
不叫免组疫化啊
Do you even understand that term?
你听懂了没有
[You all come by every so often]
你们这隔三岔五地
[to bring me food.]
来给我送吃的
It's been a blessing
我胃呀
for my stomach.
是真享福
[I'm so content.]
潇洒得很
Look at how round it's gotten.
你看这吃得滚圆的
For your information,
我跟你说
today there's more than just food.
今天不止有吃的
I brought you something special.
我给你带个好东西来
This is something I just bought.
这个是我新买的
"The Bullet! BANG!"
杀三国
Check it out.
你看看
It's "BANG! The Bullet!"
三国杀
Fine, "The Bullet! BANG! "
杀三国 杀三国
Today it's called
天王老子来
"The Bullet! BANG! "
它今天它就叫
no matter what!
杀三国
Honestly, I'm quite jealous of the
其实我还挺羡慕
relationship you have with your parents.
你和你爸妈之间的关系
My relationship with my mom
我跟我妈
was actually
其实在咱们俩好之前啊
worse before
我们俩之间的关系
the two of us started dating.
比现在还要糟糕
Before, I spent
之前我有
three years studying overseas.
三年的留学经历
Until last year,
直到去年
when she got sick,
因为她生病了
I returned to Xing city.
才回到了星城
Actually, my mom always felt
其实我妈一直就觉得
that she didn't really understand me.
她不太了解我
I feel the same way.
我也一样
I also don't know
我也不知道
how to get along with her.
该怎么跟她亲近
It's not too late, though.
还来得及
Once mom is discharged,
等咱妈出院了以后
make sure to spend more time with her.
你多花些时间陪陪她
Her health
她现在身体
is improving daily.
一天比一天好
This is a chance that fate has given you.
就是老天给你的机会
You should seize this opportunity.
你要抓住这次机会
Just don't leave yourself with regrets.
别给自己留遗憾就好
Understood.
听明白了
Boss,
领导
you're impressive.
厉害啊
Zhouyang Hotel is quite a tough challenge.
洲洋酒店可是块硬骨头
Before Mr. Jiang left,
江总走之前
he was always concerned about this.
一直惦记这事
I didn't expect that you secured the deal
没想到你刚接触合同
after making contact with them
这不到一个月
for less than a month.
就拿下了
There's an element of luck,
运气成分在
but it's mainly thanks to
主要是靠
everyone's hard work.
大家一起的努力
Yuheng, you're being modest.
师哥 你太谦虚啦
Everyone knows
所有人都知道
how difficult it is to deal with its boss.
那个老板有多难搞
You could nail him in an instant.
你这么快就能搞定
It's a testament to your hard work.
那肯定是个人业绩
Yuhui, we work in a bank, so
小唐咱们在银行工作呀
we should try to avoid discussing clients.
还是尽量不要议论客户
Especially, we shouldn't
尤其是不能
bad-mouth them.
给他们贴标签
Aren't we on the same team?
自己人吗
Just chatting, just chatting.
随便说说 随便说说
Yuheng is right.
师哥说得对
I'll be more careful.
我下次注意
Hey, boss,
领导
since we've just landed such a major deal,
谈这么大个业务
shouldn't we...
晚上是不是得搞点
How about a dinner?
庆功宴
How about tonight!
择日不如撞日就今晚
Tomorrow is the weekend,
明天周末
and I need to take my mom back home
我得带我妈
to pay respects at my dad's grave.
去老家去扫墓去
I'll need to head back tonight
今天晚上需要
to get ready.
回去准备准备
How about this:
这样吧
once the deal is finalized,
等咱们合同正式签订了
I'll take care of the celebration dinner.
庆功宴我来安排
Sounds good!
好
It's a deal then.
一言为定
I'll get back to work now.
那我先去工作了
Alright.
好
Let's get to work!
工作 工作吧
Yuheng.
师哥
Yuhui, I've told you before
小唐我说过
that in our company...
在咱们公司
Mr. Ji.
纪总
Sorry I slipped.
我刚刚太着急了忘了
I'll be careful next time.
我下次注意
Were you looking for me?
找我有事儿吗
Last time,
我们上次
we went to the hospital to visit your mom.
去医院看阿姨了
I asked the staff,
但我问了医院
and they said that each caregiver
说现在护工
has to take care of two patients.
都是一对二的
I'm worried that there might
我觉得可能
not be enough care for your mom.
会对阿姨照顾不周
How about this:
要不
I have a friend
我有一个朋友
who runs a nursing home.
他刚好是开护理医院的
Let's hire a caregiver for her.
我们帮阿姨请一个吧
I can get a discount.
我可以要折扣
The price would be much lower.
价格比医院便宜了不少
I appreciate it,
谢谢你的好意
but she's very happy with the current one.
我妈很满意现在的护工
She doesn't need it.
她不需要
Thanks anyway.
谢谢啊
Then
那
how about this:
要不这样
Starting today,
从今天开始
I'll visit her after work
我每天下班之后
to keep her company.
去医院陪阿姨聊聊天
I actually wanted to go.
我其实本来想直接去的
But I was
但是
worried you might think
我怕你会觉得我是
I was trying to get close to her
因为工作的关系
because of work.
故意接近阿姨
I just feel that
我其实就是觉得
she is getting older
阿姨年纪大了
and quite lonely.
挺孤单的
You're busy with work,
你工作忙
so I can go in your place.
我替你去
Thank you so much.
谢谢你的好意
But it's really not necessary.
没这个必要了
Why not?
为什么呀
I feel I get along
我觉得我跟阿姨
well with her.
挺聊得来的
And besides,
而且
as a mother,
当妈妈的
if she sees the right girl
如果看到孩子身边
around her son,
有合适的人出现
she should feel more at ease, right?
她应该也会放心吧
I've told you already.
该说的我都已经说了
It really isn't necessary.
真的不需要
And it's working hours right now.
而且现在是上班时间
You should get back to work.
先回去忙吧
You know very well
你明明知道
how I feel about you.
我对你是什么感觉
During work hours,
工作时间
I really shouldn't be saying this.
本来不应该说这些
But to avoid any complications,
但为了避免之后的麻烦
I think I should
我想我还是应该
make things clear.
把话说清楚
I have someone I like.
我有喜欢的人
[There's no chance for us.]
我们没有可能
Who is it?
是谁啊
Mr. Ji.
纪总
I brought the files you requested.
你要的资料拿来了
You heard everything?
听到了
You were quite firm.
态度很坚决
Good job.
表现不错
Give it back!
还给我
Limin,
立民啊
Yuheng and I
我跟小恒
haven't come to see you
这好多年没有
for years.
一起来看你了
[I used to come alone,]
以前我自己来
[and I would always ramble on]
每次都跟你絮絮叨叨地
[about him.]
说好多他的事情
Every time I'd say,
每次都跟你说
next time I'd bring him along.
下次要带他一起来
I've been fooling you all these years.
糊弄了你这么多年
Please don't hold it against me.
别怪我
[Look,]
你看
I've kept my promise,
我今天就说话算数
and I brought him to see you.
带他来看你了
Xiaoning,
筱柠
come here.
来
Let dad take a good look at you.
让爸爸看看
Limin,
立民啊
this is our daughter-in-law,
这是我们儿媳妇
Xiaoning.
筱柠
not only beautiful but also kind,
人好看心眼好
a truly wonderful girl.
是个好孩子
With her by Yuheng's side,
有她陪着小恒
we can all feel at ease.
我们都可以放心的
Go on and talk to dad.
去跟爸爸说两句话吧
I'm good.
不用
It's been a while, hasn't it?
很久没来看爸爸了吧
Go ahead.
去吧
I'm doing well.
我挺好的
Mom is doing well too.
妈也很好
We'll visit you more often from now on,
我们之后会常来看您的
dad.
爸
Take it easy.
慢点啊
It's been a long time since I came back.
这太久没回来了
Let's clean up a bit.
咱们收拾收拾
We'll manage for tonight.
今天晚上将就一晚
Family photo, mom?
全家福 妈
This was taken
那是小恒
on Yuheng's eighth birthday.
八岁生日的时候拍的
We took it in the yard.
在院子里拍的
When you were little, you didn't
你小时候
have the qualities of an old cadre at all.
可没有老干部的潜质啊
Mom,
妈
the filling for your dumplings
你这饺子馅弄得
smells amazing.
可真香啊
I can smell it
我离那么老远
from so far away.
都能闻着香味
No wonder Yuheng loves it.
怪不得昱恒喜欢呢
I gave you the recipe.
那配料都给你了
You filmed the whole process too.
过程你也都拍了
You're a smart girl;
你那么聪明
you'll master it after a couple of tries.
琢磨两次就会了
He'll definitely prefer the ones you make.
你包的他肯定更喜欢
I don't have that kind of confidence.
我可没这个自信
Didn't you just mention?
您刚才不是说了吗
When he was little,
他小时候
even if
吃两口
there were just two drops
就哪怕是
less of sesame oil,
少放了两滴香油
he could taste the difference.
都能吃出来
Mine definitely can't compete with yours.
我肯定不行
Back then,
那会儿啊
whenever I made dumplings,
我只要一包饺子
he would invite
他就招呼
his friends
玩得好的朋友
over to eat.
到家里来吃
[All boys.]
全是男孩
[That was during their growth spurts.]
那都是长身体的时候
[Once my dumplings were done,]
我这饺子一出锅
they'd be gone in the blink of an eye.
一眨眼就没了
Then
然后
they would say he
他们就说他
[was tall,]
说他个子高啊
[and it was all thanks to my dumplings.]
都是让饺子给催的
When he was in middle school,
他初中的时候啊
he was one of
那个头在班上
the tallest in class.
是数一数二的
He loved playing basketball back then.
那会儿爱打球
Every day after school,
每天放学呢
he would play for an hour or two.
都要打那么一两个小时
[With all that exercise,]
运动量大了
[it was hard for him to gain weight.]
人就不容易胖了
For a while, he looked
有一段时间看着呀
like he was malnourished.
就跟营养不良一样
He would look in the mirror and say,
他自己照照镜子还说呢
''Why do I look like a bean sprout?''
我怎么像颗豆芽菜
Mom, hearing you talk about him as a kid,
妈我听您说他小时候
makes me feel he was quite fun and cute.
感觉很逗很可爱
He seems like a totally different guy now.
跟现在好像不是一个人
After his dad passed away,
他爸走了以后
I became
我跟他
much more distant from him.
是疏远了很多
[Now that I think about it,]
现在想想
[the only memories]
脑子里面
[I can recall are]
能回忆得起来的
just a few moments from his childhood.
就他小时候这点事
[These days,]
现在啊
you understand him much better than me.
你比妈要了解他多了
Mom, look,
妈 你看
this one turned out pretty good, right?
这个包得还可以吧
This one is good.
这个还行
Come on,
来
let's light the candles.
我们点蜡烛过生日
Come on.
来吧
Blow out the candles.
吹蜡烛
After that,
吹完蜡烛
we'll eat the cake!
我们吃蛋糕啦
Sounds good!
好
But you haven't made a wish yet.
这还没许愿呢
You shouldn't blow out the candles.
怎么就吹蜡烛啦
You two!
你们这爷俩真是的
Then I'll make a wish now.
那我现在就许
OK.
对
- We forgot to make a wish. - I hope
我们忘许愿了 我希望
I will eat
我能天天吃到
dumplings made by mom every day.
妈妈包的饺子
Let her make dumplings every day.
天天让妈妈包饺子
That would wear mom out!
那不把妈妈累坏了
Let's change it, OK?
咱们换一个好不好
Then I wish for dad and mom
那我希望爸爸妈妈
to live long lives.
能长命百岁
Our family
我们一家
will always be together.
永远生活在一起
That's a wonderful wish!
这个愿望好啊
Then this wish must
那这个愿望就一定要
come true,
心想事成
right?
对不对
Come on,
来
let's take a picture.
我们拍张照
Come on, Yuheng,
来 昱恒
Smile!
笑呀
Come on.
来
Happy birthday!
生日快乐
Mom,
妈
why aren't you asleep yet?
怎么还没睡啊
Is the bed uncomfortable?
床不舒服吗
Not at all.
没有
I slept the whole time
来的时候
on the way.
路上睡了一路
Now I just can't fall asleep.
现在睡不着了
Did I wake you up?
是吵醒你了
No,
没
I just happened to take a few
我正好接了几个
calls from work.
工作电话
What's this?
这是
This is something your dad left.
你爸爸留下来的东西
I couldn't sleep,
睡不着
so I took it out.
拿出来看看
This photo
这张照片
and the one next to it
和里边那张
were taken on the same day.
是同一天拍的
Your dad
你爸爸呀
always kept it in his wallet,
一直把它放在钱包里
carrying it with him.
随身带着
This was before we talked about
这是我们说起
going to Yunnan.
去云南的事之前
I made a wish at that time.
我先许了一个愿
I said,
我说
I wanted to eat
我想每天都能吃到
dumplings made by you every day.
妈妈包的饺子
Dad said no,
我爸说不行
that would wear you out.
这样你会太累了
He told me to change a wish.
他让我换一个
You actually remember all that?
你居然还记得
Back then, our family
那时候我们一家人
was so happy together.
多好啊
Actually,
其实
when we visited dad's grave today,
今天给爸爸上坟的时候
I noticed there was something on his mind.
我看出来他有心事了
Yuheng is like that;
昱恒他就是这样
sometimes,
有时候
he's like a closed-off person
就像个闷葫芦一样
not willing to share his feelings.
不爱说心里话
You need to draw him out.
你得去激发他
If you're willing, mom,
妈妈要是愿意的话
this is a good opportunity
正好趁这次机会
to talk to him.
找时间跟他聊聊
You can also ask him
也正好问问他心里
what he's really thinking.
到底怎么想的
Yuheng,
小恒
there's something
有句话
I've always wanted to ask you.
妈妈一直想问你
When your dad passed away,
你爸爸去世那会儿
deep down,
你心里
did you blame us?
是不是特别怪我们
Your dad committed suicide.
爸爸自杀了
And I was devastated.
妈妈崩溃了
[I was in despair every day.]
整天要死要活的
It's all in the past, mom.
都过去了 妈
Time has passed,
时间过去了
but that doesn't mean the pain has gone.
不代表委屈也过去了
At that time,
那时候
I was mad
我是气
at your dad
气你爸
for not sharing his struggles with us.
有苦他不跟我们说
I also resented him
我也怨他
for leaving us behind,
怨他就抛下我们
and ending it all
自己一个人
on his own.
一死了之了
[Every day,]
我这每天哪
[it was either complaints]
又是埋怨
[or sadness.]
又是伤心
That's why I didn't want you to mention him,
所以我不让你提他
nor did I want you to visit his grave.
我不让你给他扫墓
But I overlooked
但是我忽略了
that you were still a child.
你还是个孩子
A child
是个
who just lost his dad.
刚失去爸爸的孩子
At that time,
那会你
you had to study,
又要学习
take care of me,
又要照顾妈妈
and deal with everyone's
还要面对大家
comments about your dad.
对你爸的那些议论
You carried so much pain
那么多的苦
all by yourself.
你就一个人承受下来
Today,
我今天
when I was at the grave, I saw you
扫墓的时候我看见你
standing in front of me,
当着我的面
not knowing
都不知道
how to talk
用什么样的态度
to your dad.
跟你爸说话
It's all because of me back then.
都是因为当年我
All these years,
这些年
while you were studying overseas,
你在外面念书
I only know dumplings; but besides that
可是除了饺子
I don't even know
我都不知道
what else you enjoy eating.
你还爱吃什么
[I don't even know your hobbies.]
我也不知道你喜欢什么
I also don't know
也不知道
what difficulties you've experienced,
你遇到过什么困难
[or how you've managed to get through them.]
你是怎么扛过来的
Everyone says
别人都说
you're very independent.
你好独立
But I know that's
但是妈妈知道
because you have no one to depend on.
你是因为没有依靠
Yuheng,
小恒
all these years,
这么多年
mom owes you
妈妈欠你
an apology.
一个道歉
I'm really sorry.
对不起啊
These years,
这些年
you must have had a tough time.
你一个人过得很辛苦吧
Mom,
妈
you don't need to apologize.
您不用跟我说抱歉的
Because of dad's suicide,
因为爸爸的事
I did blame you both.
我确实怪过你们
I blamed him for leaving so suddenly.
怪他说走就走
I blamed you
我怪你
for not caring enough about me.
怪你不够关心我
Honestly, I really didn't understand
其实我特别不理解
why you were so devastated
为什么我爸走了
when dad was gone.
你会那么崩溃
It wasn't until I met Xiaoning
直到后来我遇到了筱柠
that I realized that true love
我才知道真正相爱的人
might really be inseparable.
可能真的离不开对方
If it weren't for me,
要不是因为我
you might have gone
可能也去
after dad, right?
找爸爸了吧
Mom,
妈
[over the years,]
这些年
you and I
咱们娘俩
have slowly grown distant.
慢慢地疏远
That's my fault.
是因为我
[I didn't give you an opportunity.]
我没有给您这个机会
I'm sorry, mom.
对不起啊妈
All these years,
这些年
you've been so lonely on your own.
你一个人也很孤单
I...
我
I've been trying
我努力地
to be your support.
成为你们的依靠
Let's work together
咱们一起
to make up for the lost time.
把失去的时光找回来
We definitely will, mom.
一定会的妈
We definitely will.
一定会的
Xiaoning, let me tell you,
筱柠我跟你说
their sunflower seeds
他们家这个瓜子味儿啊
are especially good.
特别好
Good morning.
起来啦
How was your sleep?
睡得好吗
Yeah.
我倒是还好
Why are you up so early?
怎么起那么早啊
Xiaoning said
筱柠啊
she didn't
说她昨天一个晚上
dream at all last night.
都没做梦
She slept deeply,
睡得沉
so she woke up early.
所以起得早
There's breakfast on the table.
桌上有早餐
Help yourself.
你去吃啊
Did you already eat?
你们吃过了
We all did.
我们都吃过了
Mom,
妈
did you sleep well last night?
昨天晚上您睡得还好吗
I slept quite well.
我睡得挺好的
Today, since we're free,
今天正好有时间
how about we accompany you
要不我们陪您
to walk around the town?
去镇上转转
You don't need to be with me.
你就别陪我了
Just take Xiaoning
带筱柠啊
out for a walk.
出去好好转转
As for me,
我呢
I want to
一会儿
visit the grave again later.
想再去趟墓地
It's rare for me to come back.
难得回来一趟
I want to
我呀
have a little chat
想和你爸爸
with your dad.
再说说悄悄话
Let him show you around the town.
让他带你好好转转啊
OK.
好
I see you're in a good mood today.
我看你今天心情不错
What's up?
怎么了
Did you win the lottery?
中彩票了
I was chatting with mom last night.
昨天晚上跟妈聊天
Didn't you hear us?
你不是听到了吗
I didn't hear anything.
我可没听到
I slept really deeply last night.
我昨天睡得可沉了
I didn't hear a thing.
什么都没听到
Really?
是吗
Then when I
那我昨天
got back to my room.
回到房间的时候
Why did I suddenly see a
怎么突然看到一个
shadow rushing into the bed?
飞奔上床的影子
Wasn't that you?
不是你
Were we haunted or something?
闹鬼了
Don't scare me, OK?
你别吓唬人行不行
I'm not the kind of girl
我不是那种
who eavesdrops on others.
偷听别人说话的人
Last night, mom said
昨天晚上妈说
she's feeling much better.
她身体状态好很多了
This time when we go back,
这次回去
we should arrange for her discharge.
咱们给她办个出院手续
We can take her home.
可以接她回家了
Really?
真的
No wonder
怪不得
today she wanted to go alone
今天 要一个人
to chat with dad and share some whispers.
去找爸聊天说点悄悄话
That's good.
好事
Are you wondering
是不是想问
what happened
我爸当年
to my dad back then?
到底发生了什么
I do want to ask,
我是想问
but
但是
it's up to you whether you want to share.
你说不说都行
I understand
我知道
this is a scar in your heart.
这是你心里的一个伤疤
I'll listen when you're ready to talk.
等你想说的时候我再听
It's cool.
不碍事
If it's something you want to know,
只要是你想听的
I'll let you know for sure.
我都可以告诉你
Let's go.
走
Dad also worked
爸爸当年
at a bank back then.
也是在银行工作的
But later he got involved in
但是后来他卷入了一起
a case of illegal loan.
非法贷款的案子
At that time, the entire
那时候整个银行的
mortgage process
放贷流程
was very irregular.
都非常不正规
His old neighbor
他的老邻居
ran a small factory.
经营了一家小工厂
Later, to raise money,
后来为了筹钱
he used a shady contract
通过阴阳合同的方式
to borrow a large sum
向我爸的银行
from my dad's bank.
贷了很大一笔钱
Later, this factory
再到后来这个厂子
went bankrupt
因为经营不善
due to mismanagement.
就倒闭了
That guy
这个人
absconded with the money.
携款潜逃
My dad really wanted
我爸就很想
to recover that money.
把这笔钱给追回来
But unexpectedly, the guy's parents
但是没想到对方的父母
threatened to kill themselves.
以死相逼
They also claimed that
还说整件事情
my dad received a huge kickback.
我爸爸收了巨额的回扣
They used sleeping pills to
他们用吃安眠药的方式
fight against my dad.
跟我爸对抗
[They replaced the sleeping pills]
他们把安眠药
[with vitamins.]
换成了维生素
[They were completely unharmed,]
整个人是毫发无伤
[but stayed in the hospital,]
但一直都住在医院里
[pretending to be sick.]
装病
[They also claimed that the]
还说整件事情的
[instigator of the whole thing]
始作俑者
[was my dad.]
就是我爸
[At that time, this whole thing]
当时这件事
[became widely known.]
闹的是人尽皆知
[My dad couldn't even explain himself.]
我爸是有理都说不清
[He became the focus of]
也成为了街坊邻居
[gossip among neighbors.]
茶余饭后谈论的焦点
Yuheng,
小恒
something bad happened!
不好了 不好了
It's your dad!
你爸爸出事了
He's covered in blood!
身上全是血呀
Go home, hurry!
赶紧回去看看
[I don't remember how far]
我不记得那天
[I ran that day,]
我跑了多远
[nor how long I ran.]
也不记得那天跑了多久
[I can only remember that when I]
我只能记得那天
[got to the hospital,]
我跑到医院的时候
[I heard my mom's cries.]
我妈的哭喊声
[My dad was]
我爸是个自尊心
[a proud man.]
很强的人
[He really wanted to prove]
他特别想要证明
[his innocence.]
自己的清白
So one spring evening,
于是春天的一个傍晚
he chose to jump off a building.
他选择了跳楼
He chose to end his life
他选择了用自杀的方式
to clear his name.
洗刷了自己的冤屈
But after he passed away,
但是他走了以后
my mom fell apart.
我妈她崩溃了
For a long time,
在很长的一段时间里
she was on the verge of a breakdown.
我妈都处在崩溃的边缘
She couldn't
根本就没有办法
live a normal life at all.
正常地过日子
So when we met
所以我们在天台
on the rooftop,
见面那次
it was during that time.
就是那个时期
It was.
是
At that time, I felt like
那时候我感觉
all the students in school
全校的同学
were talking about me.
好像都在议论我
They were looking down on me.
应该说是鄙夷我吧
So during that time,
所以那段时间
I often went to the rooftop alone,
我经常一个人去天台
doing nothing,
什么都不做
just sitting there,
就坐在那里
looking into the distance.
看着远方
I didn't know how to
我也不知道未来的路
navigate my future.
到底应该怎么走
Watching the sunset on the rooftop,
在天台上看着晚霞
it felt like that day
就像是那天
when my dad committed suicide.
我爸自杀的时候那样
Actually, I really hoped
其实我特别希望
this was all a dream.
这是一场梦
When I got home from school,
放学回到家里
I wished my dad and mom
我爸我妈
could greet me
能够说说笑笑地
with smiles and laughter.
去迎接我
I misunderstood back then.
结果还被我误会了
I thought you were going to jump off.
我以为你要跳楼
To be honest,
不瞒你说
I did have that thought at that time.
那时候有过这个想法
But when I thought about
但是一想到
how devastated my mom was,
我妈那么崩溃
I knew I couldn't do that.
我知道我不能那么做
So those days when I wanted to die
所以那段想死
but couldn't, and they
又不能死的日子
were the darkest moments
是我人生当中
of my life.
最灰暗的一刻
So you really saved me.
所以确实是你救了我
You brought light
也让我的生活里
into my life.
照进来了一束光
It turns out our fate
原来我们俩的缘分
started from that moment.
从那个时候就开始了
And
而且
thanks to you,
也多亏了有你
you were the only one
你是那时候唯一一个
who cared about me back then.
关心我的人
So many years have passed,
这么多年都过去了
I really should
我确实应该
thank you for it.
跟你说声谢谢的
You don't need to thank me.
谢什么
It was nothing.
我举手之劳
Not to mention I got something in return.
而且我也不亏啊
Aren't you
你现在
devoted to me now?
不是以身相许了吗
Later on, I became determined
再到后来我就立志
to work for the compliance department.
想要到内控合规部工作
I was somewhat
多少也是
influenced by my dad's incident.
受了我爸的影响
I wish I could put in more effort
我希望能够再努力一点
to bring about
能够让整个行业的流程
greater regulation
变得更规范
and transparency in the industry.
也更透明
Even if I could only contribute
哪怕我只能做
a tiny bit,
一点点的贡献
perhaps I could help prevent
说不定就能
a family from experiencing tragedy.
阻止一个家庭的悲剧了
So,
所以
you had
你从高中的时候
already made
就已经
this decision back in high school.
做好这个决定了
I just feel it's a shame
只是我觉得很可惜
that dad never got to see me
爸爸他并没有看到我
working in a bank.
进到银行系统
He also couldn't see me transition from
也没能看到我从内控
internal control to the business side.
到了业务口
And he never got to see
更没能亲眼见到
his daughter-in-law in person.
他的儿媳妇
This doll is so adorable!
这个娃娃真可爱
Yeah.
对
Let's put her in the room
这个应该放到房间里
as a decoration.
摆起来
It really is quite adorable.
是挺可爱的
I just thought of a place.
我想到一个地方
Let me take you there.
带你去
Sounds good!
好
Let's go.
走
Here, try this.
来试试
Just one tap.
点一下
Wow, you really know how to do this.
原来你真的会弄啊
I thought
我以为
you were kidding.
你就说着玩的呢
I used to do it often in middle school.
中学的时候我经常来做
Back then,
那个时候
studying was really exhausting,
学习学得很累
so this was my way to unwind.
这个就当是解压了
But after starting college,
不过上了大学以后
I pretty much stopped.
基本上就没做了
[It turns out that]
原来那个白月光
[clay doll]
泥塑娃娃
[was made by him personally.]
是他亲手做的
Well done.
真不错
Actually, in our town,
其实我们这个镇上啊
the most renowned products
最有名的
are handmade crafts.
就是手工艺制品
Glass, clay sculptures, and weaving.
玻璃 泥塑 藤编
The owner of this shop
这家店的老板呀
is my aunt.
是我表姨
When I was a kid,
小的时候
my mom often brought me here.
我妈经常带我来
Why did you
那你干吗
work at a bank?
要去银行工作呀
Wouldn't that be
这么好的手艺
a waste of talent?
不是浪费了吗
You should have developed those skills;
好好培养培养
who knows, you might even have
说不定还能
become an artist.
成为一个艺术家
What's going on
小脑袋
in that little head of yours?
成天在想什么
So,
怎么样
what else would you like to make?
想好再做一个什么
Yeah,
想好了
I want to make one
做一个
for our entire family.
大的全家福
With my dad and mom,
有我爸我妈
your dad and mom,
你爸你妈
and the two of us.
还有我们两个
Leave no one behind.
一个都不能少
That's quite a challenge.
这人可不是很好做呀
And you have to make six of them at once.
而且一次性要做六个
You could do it.
你会做
Why wouldn't I be able to?
我为什么不会做啊
I can handle it.
我可以的
Don't mind me.
你不要管我
You focus on yours; I'll focus on mine.
你做你的我做我的
Just don't disturb me.
别来打扰我啊
Then I'll leave you be.
那我不管你了
Go.
走吧
[How's it coming along?]
做得怎么样了
All done!
做好了
Take a look.
你看
That looks great!
还不错呀
Of course!
那当然
Thank you, aunt.
谢谢表姨
You're welcome!
不客气
Take it home
拿回家
and place it somewhere safe.
放在不容易碰到的地方
Keep it
摆好
out of direct sunlight.
避免阳光直晒
Got it!
好
This town
以后啊
will also be your home.
这也是你的老家了
Whenever you're free,
有空啊
make sure to visit your mom
多跟你的婆婆
and explore the town.
回到镇上逛逛
Over the years,
这些年啊
the young people have all moved away,
年轻人一个个走出去
leaving only us old folks behind.
就剩我们这些老东西了
By the way, aunt,
对了表姨
what happened to that family
对过那家
across the street that made glass?
做玻璃的兄弟去哪儿了
They struck it rich
他们去年哪
last year
飞黄腾达
and started a company in the city,
到市里开公司了
[specializing in home glass installations.]
专做家装落地玻璃
[I heard from their parents]
听他爸妈说
that the two brothers
两兄弟呀
plan to double their business this year.
计划今年把公司翻一番
They want to grow the company.
做大公司呢
Grow the company, huh?
做大公司啊
Aunt,
表姨
could you
你方便
give me their phone number?
把他们的电话给我吗
If they want to expand,
他想要做大公司
they'll need funding, right?
需要资金吧
If they need a loan,
如果要贷款的话
they can come to me.
可以来找我
You're a pro at spotting chances!
真会把握机会啊
That's called professional sensitivity.
这是职业敏感度
[Of course!]
有什么不方便的
[We're all]
一个镇上的
family here.
自家人
I'll send you the number later.
回头我把号码发给你
Thank you, aunt!
谢谢表姨
You're
这孩子
welcome, sweetie.
真是客气
Pay up.
付钱呀
I'm not taking your money.
我可不要啊
Yuheng rarely comes back.
小恒难得回来一趟
I won't take his money.
我可不能收他的钱
Yuheng,
小恒啊
in the future,
以后啊
bring your mom back more often
多带妈妈回来
so we old friends
让我们老姐妹
could get a chance
有机会
to catch up.
聊聊天就行了
Sure, no problem!
行没问题
OK,
那我就
thank you, aunt.
谢谢表姨了
No problem.
客气啥
Alright.
好
We're off.
那我们走了
Goodbye, aunt!
表姨再见
See you, aunt.
走了表姨
Xiaoning, you are really talented in this.
筱柠这手真巧啊
They look fantastic.
真好看
Mom, you don't know.
妈您是不知道
Xiaoning not only
筱柠呢
has skillful hands,
不光是手巧
but also a creative mind.
心思还很活络
When we
刚刚我们
were making the clay sculptures,
做这个泥塑的时候
she was thinking about finding clients.
还想着发展一下客户呢
Don't embarrass me
当着妈的面
in front of mom,
你就别寒碜我了
That's alright.
没关系
I just
我呀
sit here,
就这么坐着
watching the sunset,
看看夕阳
enjoying the evening breeze,
吹吹晚风
and listening to you
再听你们呀
chat and joke around.
聊天逗趣
It makes me really happy.
开心着呢
Mom,
妈
when we are free,
等有时间
let's go on a road trip
咱们自驾游
up north
北上
to the grasslands.
去大草原吧
I know you'll love it.
您肯定喜欢
That sounds great.
好啊
Once I'm feeling better,
等我身体养得差不多了
we should
咱们啊
invite your dad and mom
叫上你爸爸妈妈
and go on a
咱们一家人
family road trip.
出去自驾游去
Maybe I should learn to drive.
要不我去学个车吧
Is it still
我
possible at
现在这个年龄
my age?
还能学吗
Of course you can, mom.
当然可以了妈
Then
那
I'll help you learn.
我陪妈练车
Sounds good.
好
By the way,
对了
mom,
妈
Yuheng's going on a business trip tomorrow
明天昱恒要出差
for two to three days
两到三天
to sign a contract.
签一个合同
When he gets back,
等他回来了以后
we'll take you home from the hospital.
我们就去医院接您回家
You'll officially be home.
正式回家了
Wonderful!
太好了
Where's yours? Let me see yours!
你的呢 我看看
If you ask me, working in the bank
要我说你干这行啊
is a waste of your talents.
可惜了
If you developed your skills further,
要是再培养培养
you might become a
说不定能成为一个
great artist.
大艺术家
How does mine look?
看我的怎么样
It looks fantastic!
好看
This red umbrella...
这把红伞
Puling?
浦龄
Isn't this from my dad's company?
这不是我爸公司的吗
I remember you have one as well.
我记得你也有一把
Maybe
说不定
this one is the one.
这把就是那把
Isn't this just a
这不就是一个
promotional umbrella?
赠送的伞吗
Why do you like it so much?
你怎么那么喜欢它
This is the one I used when I picked you
这是我第一次
up from work for the first time.
接你下班时候的伞
Don't you remember it?
不记得了
I remember it.
记得
Of course I remember.
当然要记得